Kate M Johnson

PhD Candidate

I am a health economist and health outcomes researcher interested in improving care for chronic diseases. My research has two broad themes: 1) evidence generation to understand decision trajectory and individualize patient care, and 2) whole disease modelling to evaluate healthcare policies. I use empirical analysis of clinical studies, big data analytics, and simulation modeling to answer clinical and policy questions.

Education

- 2016- PhD Pharmaceutical Sciences. University of British Columbia
- 2013-2015 MSc Biology. University of British Columbia
- 2008-2013 BSc Biology. University of Alberta

Awards

- 2019 Institute of Health Services and Policy Research Travel Award, Canadian Institutes of Health Research, \$1,500.
- 2019 **Symposium Travel Award**, Canadian Agency for Drugs and Technologies in Health, \$1,650.
- 2019 John H. McNeill Award, University of British Columbia, \$2,300.
- 2019 Santosh M. Wasam Travel Award, University of British Columbia, \$1,000.
- 2019, 2018 Outstanding Service Award, Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences.
- 2018, 2017 Institute of Circulatory and Respiratory Health Travel Award, Canadian Institutes of Health Research, \$2000.
 - 2017 Four Year Doctoral Fellowship, University of British Columbia, \$72,800.
 - 2017 Studentship Award, The Canadian Lung Association, \$42,000.
 - 2016 **Douglas and Jean Bailey Award**, University of British Columbia, \$1,700.

- 2016 Graduate Student Award, Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, \$2,000.
- 2014 Bert Hoffmeister Award, University of British Columbia, \$3,500.
- 2014 Canadian Graduate Scholarship, Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada, \$17,500.
- 2014 Van Tyne Research Award, American Ornithologists Union, \$2,500.
- 2014 Hesse Graduate Award, University of British Columbia, \$1,800.
- 2013 BRITE Research Award, University of British Columbia, \$10,000.
- 2013 Faculty of Forestry Graduate Award, University of British Columbia, \$5,000.
- 2012 Undergraduate Research Award, Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada, \$4,500.

Publications

Journal Articles

- 2019 Development and validation of the Evaluation Platform In COPD (EPIC): a population-based outcomes model of COPD for Canada, M Sadatsafavi, S Ghanbarian, A Adibi, KM Johnson, JM FitzGerald, ..., Medical Decision Making.
- 2018 Characterizing undiagnosed chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis, KM Johnson, S Bryan, S Ghanbarian, DD Sin, M Sadatsafavi, Respiratory Research.
- 2018 The association between previous and future severe exacerbations of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: Updating the literature using robust statistical methodology, M Sadatsafavi, H Xie, M Etminan, KM Johnson, JM FitzGerald, ..., PloS one.
- 2018 Long-term effects of inhaled corticosteroids on bone mineral density in older women with asthma or COPD: a registry-based cohort study, KM Johnson, W Chen, JM FitzGerald, M Sadatsafavi, WD Leslie, Archives of Osteoporosis.

- 2018 The diagnostic performance of patient symptoms in screening for COPD, KM Johnson, WC Tan, J Bourbeau, DD Sin, M Sadatsafavi, Respiratory Research.
- 2018 A systematic review of the adverse events and economic impact associated with oral corticosteroids in asthma, K Al Efraij, KM Johnson, D Wiebe, M Sadatsafavi, JM FitzGerald, Journal of Asthma.
- 2018 The costs of misdiagnosed asthma in a longitudinal study of the general population, B Ng, M Sadatsafavi, A Safari, JM Fitzgerald, KM Johnson, bioRxiv.
- 2018 Heterogeneity in the respiratory symptoms of patients with mild-to-moderate COPD, KM Johnson, A Safari, WC Tan, J Bourbeau, JM FitzGerald, M Sadatsafavi, International Journal of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease.
- 2017 Stability of asthma symptom control in a longitudinal study of mild-moderate asthmatics, KM Johnson, JM FitzGerald, H Tavakoli, W Chen, M Sadatsafavi, The Journal of Allergy and Clinical Immunology: In Practice.
- 2018 Demographic consequences of invasion by a native, controphic competitor to an insular bird population, KM Johnson, RR Germain, CE Tarwater, JM Reid, P Arcese, Oecologia.
- 2016 Nest defense and parental investment in Song Sparrows (Melospiza melodia), N Morrell, KM Johnson, CE Tarwater, P Arcese, Canadian Journal of Zoology.
- 2014 Demographic effects on fruit set in the dioecious shrub Canada buffaloberry (Shepherdia canadensis), KM Johnson, SE Nielsen, PeerJ.

Conference Publications

- 2019 Healthcare services use before COPD diagnosis: a registry-based longitudinal cohort study, KM Johnson, A Khakban, S Bryan, D Sin, M Sadatsafavi, Canadian Respiratory Conference.
- 2018 Drivers of respiratory symptoms in COPD patients, KM Johnson, A Safari, WC Tan, J Bourbeau, M Sadatsafavi, European Respiratory Congress.

- 2018 The discriminatory capacity of symptoms to distinguish undiagnosed COPD from non-COPD, KM Johnson, WC Tan, J Bourbeau, M Sadatsafavi, European Respiratory Congress.
- 2018 Characterizing undiagnosed chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis, KM Johnson, S Bryan, S Ghanbarian, M Sadatsafavi, American Thoracic Society International Conference.
- 2017 Stability of asthma symptom control in a longitudinal study of mild-moderate asthmatics, KM Johnson, JM FitzGerald, H Tavakoli, w Chen, M Sadatsafavi, Canadian Respiratory Conference.

Presentations

- 2019 Evaluating strategies for early detection of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease, Network of Alberta Health Economists Thesis Throwdown Competition, 1st place.
- 2019 **Healthcare resource use before COPD diagnosis**, Canadian Respiratory Research Network Annual General Meeting, Best trainee presentation.
- 2018 Using respiratory symptoms to distinguish between undiagnosed COPD and non-COPD, Canadian Respiratory Research Network Annual General Meeting, 3rd Best trainee presentation.
- 2018 Characterizing undiagnosed chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: a systematic review and meta analysis, British Columbia Heart and Lung FEST.
- 2017 Stability of asthma symptom control in a longitudinal study of mild-moderate asthmatics, Canadian Respiratory Research Network Annual General Meeting.

Teaching Experience

- 2019 Data Wrangling for Health Outcomes Research in R Workshop, International Society for Pharmacoeconomics and Outcomes Research, University of British Columbia Student Chapter.
 - o Constructed and led a 3 hour workshop on the fundamentals of data manipulation in R using the tidyverse. Course materials can be found at github.com/KateJohnson/ISPORDataWrangling

- 2019 Interactive Activity Workshop (Epidemiology 101), 3rd year Pharmacy Students, University of British Columbia.
 - Lectured and led students through a three hour workshop on hypothesis testing, and calculating odd ratios and risk ratios from contingency tables.
- 2019 Graduate Teaching Assistant DSCI 554 (Experimentation and Causal Inference), Master of Data Science Program, University of British Columbia.
 - Held weekly office hours. Guided students through interactive lab exercises, and designing and conducting a study to explore a topic of interest in data science.
- 2018 Graduate Teaching Assistant DSCI 552 (Statistical Inference and Computation), Master of Data Science Program, University of British Columbia.
 - $\circ\,$ Held weekly office hours. Guided students through interactive lab exercises in R and GitHub.
- 2016 Instructional Skills Workshop, Centre for Teaching, Learning and Technology, University of British Columbia.
 - Three day professional development workshop designed to help graduate students enhance their teaching skills.

Service

Manuscript Reviews

European Journal of Health Economics (1).

Journal of Allergy and Clinical Immunology: In Practice (1).

Scientific Reports (1).

Respiratory Research (2).

2018 Canadian Agency for Drugs and Technologies in Health Symposium (Abstracts).

Leadership

- 2019-2020 Director of Education. ISPOR University of British Colombia Student Chapter
- 2017-2019 Organizing Committee. Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences Research Symposium

Mentorship

- 2018-2019 **Graduate Student Mentorship Program**, 2 Mentees, Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, University of British Columbia.
 - $\circ~$ I provide advice and resources to first year graduate students.
 - 2018 Summer Student Research Program, 1 Mentee, Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, University of British Columbia.
 - I was the primary supervisor of an undergraduate student (B. Ng), who conducted a
 research project on the costs of misdiagnosed asthma. I supervised the study design,
 analysis of the data, and writing the manuscript. I am senior author of the resulting
 manuscript (Ng 2018).

- 2014-2015 **Undergraduate Student Research Award**, 2 Mentees, Faculty of Forestry, University of British Columbia.
 - I supervised two undergraduate students during a season of data collection. I helped develop and publish an independent research project with one of the students (Morrell 2016).